<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Kleis Euangeliou tou mystikou, or, A key of the doctrines contained in this book for the better perusal thereof with some additions of Christs being heir of all things ... : and Abrahams being heir of the world ... : and of promised and covenant mercies to the father ... / by W.S. ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3398</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34220</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14147956</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14147956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59927)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Kleis Euangeliou tou mystikou, or, A key of the doctrines contained in this book for the better perusal thereof with some additions of Christs being heir of all things ... : and Abrahams being heir of the world ... : and of promised and covenant mercies to the father ... / by W.S. ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10, 4, 4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First four words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kingdom of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102106:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR A KEY of the DOCTRINES contained in this BOOK for the better peruſal thereof: With ſome Additions</p>
            <p>Of Chriſts being Heir of all things, in his three-fold Right, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Abrahams</hi> being Heir of the World, <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>And of Promiſed and Covenanted Mercies to the Fathers ſince that firſt Promiſe made for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Generations, <bibl>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Castle</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102106:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102106:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>OR</hi> The Key of the Doctrine of the Kingdom of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the better peruſal of this Work. <hi>Firſt, in more brief Aſſertions: Secondly, in their larger Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> The briefer Aſſertions.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat the ſubſtance of theſe Doctrines contained in this Work, is ſet down [for Information of all ſorts, and to remove miſtakes] in the two folded leaves after the <hi>Everlasting Goſpel</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they yeild no ground of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to Magiſtrates; yea ſuch preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice is inconſiſtent with the Tenour of them. <hi>See Word written page laſt, beſides Letters, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Their Scripture Evidence is holy, juſt and good, containing an excellent part of the Goſpel of Chriſt. <hi>See the</hi> 12. <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, &amp; the S. convincing Arguments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. All holy Prophets and Pen-men of Sacred Scriptures give witneſs to them, and chiefly, the greatly beloved Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the beloved Evangeliſt <hi>John</hi> the firſt declared, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. The 2d from the Order or Series of the <hi>Rev.</hi> in the Letter to Mr. <hi>Cal. March</hi> 20. 1664. and in the <hi>Irenicon</hi> p. 26, 27. and from the Scheme of the <hi>Rev.</hi> and Summaries and Abridgement of <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophetical Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and the Parallels of both Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies in both books.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is given by Chriſt to his Church as an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly more full Expoſition of many things in <hi>Daniel,</hi> before ſhut up to Men and Angels; and Sealed until that time of the End wherein Chriſt ſo revealed them; Which ſaid book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is a Divine myſtical Comment of ſuch hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den part of <hi>Daniel. See thence three ſorts of Learned Mens miſtakes page</hi> 30. <hi>of our General Title page; as may be manifeſt by our ſaid book of Parallels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. That there are eight ſeveral ſences of Chriſts comings in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> two before his <hi>Aſcention</hi> and ſix ſince. Firſt, in his coming in our fleſh, as in that faithful &amp; true ſaying, <hi>Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. 2dly, when, (as the Miniſter of <hi>Circumciſion, Rom.</hi> 15. he <hi>came to his own,</hi> viz. the <hi>Jews, and they received him not,</hi> John 1.11.) The other ſix ſince he Aſcended, are handled <hi>page</hi> 41. to <hi>page</hi> 46. of our <hi>Ireni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, &amp;c. See the laſt page of the Word writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning the laſt coming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. That Chriſts ſaid Appearance and Reign the thouſand years, will both be perſonal, may thence be plainly evident, in that he (then) according to Scripture expreſſions, is ſaid to come to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then as well as at the laſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judgment, both the Judgment is ſaid to be ſet, and the Books to be opened; which are the Scriptural decypherings of both Judicial acts, and quick and dead at both ſaid Acts are judged, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and of the ſame time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. upon the ſounding of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, Trumpet, when the Kingdoms of the world become the Kingdoms of Chriſt, and he is praiſed by the twenty four El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, for taking to himſelf his great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and reigning: they praiſe him not only that he had ſo judged, that is, rewarded his ſervants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his name both ſmall and great, but that he had judged them that deſtroyed the earth; having ſo judged the <hi>Whore,</hi> and (probably) the <hi>Turk</hi> alſo: hence ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi> of the ſame time, <hi>who will judge the quick and dead at his Appearance and his Kingdome,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1. and in the ſaid table of times, <hi>chap.</hi> 20 4. to <hi>verſe</hi> 11. paſſeth the thouſand years of Chriſts ſaid reign, and Satans binding, &amp; the little ſpace for his attempt with his laſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102106:3"/> 
                  <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> before the laſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Judgment, moſt clearly and fully ſet down with a great deal of diſtinct exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of order; &amp; at the laſt ſaid Judgment, the quick (namely the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi>) are conſumed with fire, and all the Dead judged when the Jugdment was ſet and the Books opened, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the end. So Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> Mr. <hi>Archer,</hi> Mr. <hi>Maton</hi> and others; but eſpecially Dr. <hi>Homes,</hi> a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of whoſe main Texts of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I ſhall only here quote, referring the Readers to <hi>p.</hi> 78. of his <hi>R. R.</hi> (which here I ſet down for the benefit of ſuch as may not (haply) ſee his book) where firſt he hath ten Texts for Chriſts perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the <hi>New Teſtament, viz. Joh.</hi> 19.37. expounded by <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. unto which he addeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 1. to 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.38, 39<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.3. Alſo ſive Texts in the <hi>Old Teſtament, Dan.</hi> 7.11. to the end, (which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſtiles the Mother text for it) <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5, 6. <hi>Zac.</hi> 2 10, 11, 12. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.14. and beſides his judicious and learned Explications of them all, a diſcourſe is added thereof after the ſaid texts: And after his opening of many Propheſies in their order (as they ſtand Recorded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) to this and other the like purpoſes, reſpecting theſe ſaid Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines very largly and learnedly out of the <hi>Old Teſtament:</hi> He then adds, <hi>page</hi> 377. twelve texts of holy Scripture more out of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> for Chriſts perſonal reign, <hi>viz. Mat.</hi> 24.13, 14. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31, 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21.24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.28, 29, 30. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.25, 26, 27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1, to 29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.16, 17, 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25, 26, 27, 28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18, 19, <hi>chap.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all which Scriptures he ſaith ſo much, there, and elſe where, that I judge may ſatisfie all impartial and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſtians; and thoſe Texts which prove his perſonal appearance, will alſo prove his perſonal reign as we ſaid, which is the end wherefore he then appears as the Great King of Kings to ſit on <hi>Davids</hi> Throne and to do his Kingly work, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying and ſlaying his Enemies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. and of rewarding his faithful ſervants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his name both ſmall and great <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. &amp; 22.12. <hi>So performing the mercies promiſed to the fore-fathers,</hi> Luke 1.72. <hi>and the Oath which he ſware unto our father</hi> Abraham, <hi>&amp;c</hi> &amp; <hi>Luke</hi> 2.32. <hi>to be the glory of his people</hi> Iſrael, of which Scripture is aboundant [<hi>See Sir</hi> Henry Finch <hi>his book forenamed</hi>] but note eſpecially the time when the Kingdoms of all Nations ſhall be given to him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all Kingdoms (to make it yet more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident) under the whole heavens ſhall ſerve and obey him, <hi>v.</hi> 27. with <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. <hi>chap.</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſa.</hi> 24.23. alſo our Tract on <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. with our paper of <hi>Sept.</hi> 27. 1664. <hi>p.</hi> 27, 28. of our <hi>Prodrom</hi> or <hi>Forerunne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. That theſe Doctrines are ſummari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Scriptural explications of two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith, <hi>vix.</hi> of Chriſts coming to judgment, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and of his raiſing of the juſt at the firſt bleſſed and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reſurrection, <hi>v</hi> 5, 6.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That the <hi>Jews</hi> averſneſs from ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſts grace to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before <hi>Peters</hi> Viſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 11. ſhould caution the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians againſt oppoſing thoſe Doctrines from Scripture, containing the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtronger title by far, to much more ample mercies. [<hi>See that renownedly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and religious Gentleman Sir</hi> Henry Finch <hi>his book of the calling of the</hi> Jews, <hi>and his Epiſtle to them;</hi>] and that will be when their glorious <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhall come to thoſe who are beloved for their Fathers ſakes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. to take away the Vail from their hearts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The reaſon Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> gave of the clouding of theſe Doctrines when Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was to ariſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to make way for his coming: The like alſo may be given for the clearing of them (in ſome meaſure) when the Date of that Man of ſin is wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, namly, to help to bring him down: I ſay, but in ſome meaſure, becauſe the Scripture gives divers hints that they will not be received by many, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.9. &amp; 21.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102106:3"/> 5. &amp; 22.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. which now appears by prevailing iniquity, by prejudice of ſome and intereſts of others, ingagements of credit, buſineſs, ſhakings of the world, many diſtractions, tentations, contrary ſeducements, and the like. <hi>See the emergent conjecture of</hi> 1666. <hi>from Chriſts Aſcention, on Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>p.</hi> 36, 37, <hi>&amp;c. from four Miſtical Numbes,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. That the Dominion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the <hi>Jews</hi> will be manifeſt (then) to be founded in grace, and to be the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whom the Lord hath bleſſed <hi>Eſ.</hi> 65.23. (probably) more eſpecially the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> as diſtinctly ſo known from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, <hi>Eſ</hi> 61.9. when they ſhall be borne in a day (ſpiritually and nationally) for the moſt part (probably) at Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance to them when his feet ſhall ſtand on mount <hi>Olivet</hi> from whence he aſcended, and then will cauſe the cleaving of the Mountain and great Vally to <hi>Azal</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Zachary c</hi> 14. foretels) and their iniquity be taken away in one day, <hi>Zac.</hi> 3.9. And as Juſtice and Judgment are now &amp; for ever the ſtability of Chriſts Throne; ſo they will be then of all other Kings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. <hi>See Foundat.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Sarah</hi> expected by Faith, their particular Shares or Lots in the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> a far of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>viz.</hi> at the Reſurrection of the Juſt, and in aſſurance thereof they would be buried there [as alſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> would have his bones] as it were to keep poſſeſſion till that time of fulfilling Gods promiſe thereof to each of them. [<hi>See p.</hi> 38, 39. of the <hi>Prodr.</hi>] therefore they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves Pilgrims. 2dly, they ſought no opportunity to return, <hi>v.</hi> 15. 3dly, they looked for that heavenly countrey of Chriſts Kingdom <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16, 17, 18, <hi>&amp;c. Gal.</hi> 3.8, 9, <hi>&amp;c. See our</hi> 15 <hi>Reaſons in</hi> New Jeru. <hi>and</hi> Prodromus <hi>p.</hi> 38.</p>
               <p n="13">13. That ſome of the Subjects of Chriſts Kingdom will be raiſed Saints, the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Reſurrection in that world, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36. others converted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in their natural life in their ſeveral conditions, as follows.</p>
               <p n="14">14. There will be accordingly two <hi>New Jeruſalems</hi> in the world, the one came down from God out of heaven <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-nymicolly,</hi> in reſpect of the Inhabitants for the time to come, being when they came down, the ſpirits of juſt men coming with Chriſt to receive their bodies, called the Bride the Lambs wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and ſo to be the Inhabitants of that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous City whoſe maker and builder is God <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. where the ſaid rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saints will behold Chriſts glory, which was by Chriſts laſt will bequeathed to them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. The other <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> will be built by men, and partly by ſtrangers, and their Kings for the uſe of ſuch as ſhall walk in the light of the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem. See</hi> Tract. <hi>on</hi> Jer. 3.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>page</hi> 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="15">15. The great diſcoveries to be made to Saints and Angels in the time of Chriſts ſaid Kingom reſpecting Scriptures, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Providences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will (probab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) much more enable both ſorts of them more excellently to ſet forth Gods praiſe to all eternity. G. Tit. page, and greater diſcoveries to be in that Millen. than in all the 6000. years before.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Scripture Theologie of that world to come in the time of the New Heavens and New Earth, is of very large conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in reſpect of the many particularities thereunto appertaining. <hi>See firſt Arg. of the Word Written, of things before the</hi> 1000. <hi>years, in them and after them, and our</hi> 31. <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> after the Tract. on</hi> Rev. 22.20. <hi>with our</hi> 12. <hi>Foundat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. The knowledge of Chriſts executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his three great Offices [as the work his Father gave him to do during the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of his Mediatorſhip] in reſpect of his Mediatorſhip in the three great Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods of the World; <hi>viz.</hi> as the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the Old Teſtament by his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſpired Meſſengers. 2dly, As the great High Prieſt in the Newe: Firſt, by his own Oblation; Secondly, by his Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion during Gods Kingdom of the Stone,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102106:4"/> wherein Chriſt appears to be the Fathers Commiſſioner to open the Sealed Book and execute the Coments thereof, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the third, he begins his own King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Mountain, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. which he went to Heaven to receive, and then to return, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof (I ſay) is of very great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to all true Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> as it is diſtinct from his particular execution of his ſaid three Offices for particular Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Souls in all times ſince mans fall; in reſpect of the particular Application of them all in their virtue and efficacie, as the Prophet, Prieſt and King of every be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving ſoul, by the powerful work of his holy Spirit. <hi>See</hi> 17. <hi>Theſ p.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>of the Prod. with the addition, p.</hi> 44, 45, 46. <hi>and eſpecially more largly handled in our Everlaſting Goſpel on</hi> Gen. 3.15.</p>
               <p n="18">18. The laſt Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and the laſt ſounding Trumpet, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52, 53. differ not only in above a 1000. years diſtance of time, but alſo in their natures and uſes. <hi>See the Series of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in the Scheme of the</hi> Revelation <hi>and the Abridgment of the</hi> Revelation <hi>and</hi> Daniel <hi>which may much help as a ſtandard [with the Parallels] to take due proportions in ſuch caſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="19">19. That there are two <hi>Gogs</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogs</hi> to be deſtroyed, the one at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the other after the little ſpace, at the end of the 1000. years. Firſt, the <hi>Pope, Dan</hi> 7.7, 8, 9, 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. with the latter part of the chap.</hi> the body of which Beaſt is to be conſumed with the burning flame (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battle. And the <hi>Turk</hi> of whom in the latter dayes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.8, 16. as to his Armie, overthrow, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, ſaving the ſixth part, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as at large ſet down in <hi>ch.</hi> 38. &amp; 39. But of the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9, 10. about the general rapture and change of all the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15, 52, 53.</p>
               <p n="20">20. That the General Rapture and Change of all the Saints about the laſt Trumpet, will be (I conceive) of them in a three-fold ſtate or condition, firſt in the natural life, to be changed in ſtead of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 2dly of Saints before raiſed, twice, ſaid to be alive and remain, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 17. 3dly, of the dead in the 1000. years, then to riſe firſt (before the wicked as others did in the ſaid time) <hi>v.</hi> 16. which Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſeems to point out.</p>
               <p n="21">21. As Chriſt our Saviour ſhould not fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh that work of Redempt. in the world which he is appointed to by his Fathers Commiſſion, manifeſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. according to his former decreed and promiſed grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> often ſince renewed to the fore-fathers, when receiving (as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31, 32, 33.) his <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom, he ſhall return from his Fathers right hand in the clouds of Heaven in his own glory, and of his Father and his holy Angels, then making his great enemies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently his footſtool, and bind Satan for the 1000. years. So taking to himſelf his great power to reign, and ſo alſo tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, outwardly and viſibly, to deliver his people from the hands of all their enemies to ſerve him without fear of them, <hi>&amp;c. Luk.</hi> 1.71, 72, 73, 74, (which ſeems to be the poſſeſſing of the Gate of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.27.) at his next coming; as well as he wrought their ſpiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption at the firſt [that none of his ſhould be loſt] and to be then the glory of his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as he hath ſince that been a Light to Lighten the <hi>Gentiles, Luke</hi> 2.72. all which are grounds of that truth. So neither ſhould God, without his doing of theſe things, perform thoſe promiſed mercies to the fore-fathers to thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent purpoſes (in the time of his ſaid Viſible and Glorious Kingdome in the world) at ſeveral times made unto them, as in divers particulars enſuing is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable; as <hi>firſt,</hi> that to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve. Secondly,</hi> to <hi>Noah. Thirdly,</hi> to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob. Fourthly,</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> will clearly manifeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102106:4"/>
               <head>Of Gods great Promiſed Mercies to the Fore-Fathers made in the Old Teſtament through Chriſt, to be fulfilled by him in the World to come, in the time of his glorious Kingdom therein.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THat all the great Promiſes and Covenants of God, made to men under the Old Teſtament, when the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had loſt his own, and his natural Seeds intereſt, were to be fulfilled by Chriſt, whom (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. God had appointed him Heir for all things, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. from a three-fold Title to be compleated in the time of his Kingdom on earth. <hi>First,</hi> God having by him Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2dly, he hath ſince purged his peoples ſins by his own bloud, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing to them all grace, and gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt therein. And 3dly, Upholding all things by his word of Divine power, and ſo diſpoſing them, that they <hi>then</hi> with him ſhould be Heirs, <hi>even joynt Heirs with Chriſt,</hi> ſaith that Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. (who was Rapt up to Paradiſe to learn Divine Myſteries after Chriſt had gloriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him at his Converſion) and as Chriſt, by that beloved, and ſo Divinely taught Diſciple <hi>John,</hi> more fully promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to all Overcomers; that they ſhall ſit with Chriſt on his Throne, <hi>viz.</hi> of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatory Kingdom even as he having over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, is now ſet down with his Father on his Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and that he will give him then power over the Nations to break them, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 2.27. but he further adds from Chriſts Warrant alſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit all things: and I will be his God, and he ſhall be my Son.</hi> Which will be obtained from Chriſt in the compleating of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion of the ſaid inheritance by our great <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in the time of his ſaid Kingdom, whereof they are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with him joynt heirs, and then with him ſhall become poſſeſſors: in reference whereunto all the ſaid Promiſes were made to the Fathers in their order and times.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt that made to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> upon their fall and ſentence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>The Seed of the Woman ſhall break the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head.</hi> Which he hath been doing ever ſince (as we ſhewed) in due order and manner appointed by the Eather, and ſtill doth, and will ſo doe; but upon his recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of his Kingdom will do it more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently, <hi>until he make his Foes,</hi> even the ſtouteſt of them, <hi>his Footſtool,</hi> Pſ. 110.1. <hi>even till the laſt enemy death ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. which will be, as Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture witneſſeth, at the compleating of his ſaid 1000. years reign, <hi>For he muſt reign,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>until he hath put all his enemies under his feet; when death the laſt enemy ſhall be destroyed,</hi> v. 26. and when all his overcomers that reigned with him before in the 1000. years, ſhall be rapt up with all Saints (in their ſeveral ſtates then) to meet him in the Aire, and thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ever be with him the Lord in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and bleſſed condition, upon the ſaid compleat breaking the Serpent <hi>[Satans]</hi> head. <hi>See our Theſ. Prodrom. p.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13. <hi>and this largely handled in our Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel on</hi> Gen. 3.15. <hi>to which I refer the Reader.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That Promiſe and Covenant that God made to <hi>Noah,</hi> through him whoſe Type he was, in ſaving his own houſe or family in the Arke, at the drowning of the Old World, as Chriſt will alſo be his Sts. ſafe Arke both at his next appearance, when as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>The Eagles will be gathered to the Carkaſs, Luke</hi> 17.38. and alſo from the laſt deſtruction of the World by fire, at the ſaid gener. rapture of all the Sts. above a 1000. years after. Now he giveth by that Covenant with <hi>Noah</hi> for himſelf, men and beaſts, preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the largeſt and and ſtrongeſt Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of preſervation of the Earth from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102106:5"/> like deſtruction, upon <hi>Noahs</hi> offering Sacrifices of the clean beaſts and fowls pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with him in the Arke. Whereupon the Lord ſmelled a ſweet ſavour [<hi>viz.</hi> through the ſaid Antetype of <hi>Noah] And the Lord ſaid in his heart: I will not again any more curſe the ground for mans ſake.</hi> And the freeneſs of his grace more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly appeared by his following reaſon, which had a contrary effect before, <hi>ch</hi> 6.5, 6. but now he will not deſtroy it, <hi>for the imagination,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.21, 22. <hi>of mans heart is evil from his youth: nor will I any more ſmite every living thing as I have done.</hi> And all this is further inlarged and illuſtrated with an ample affirmative Charter. While (ſaith the Lord <hi>[Jehovah]</hi>) or yet all the dayes of the earth, as in <hi>Heb. Seed time and Harvest, cold and heat, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter, day and night, ſhall not ceaſe.</hi> But what was a Being without a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, but miſery? Therefore in <hi>chap.</hi> 9. he largly diſtributes his Bleſſings to <hi>Noah,</hi> &amp; his Sons, to the beaſts, cattle and creeping thing, fiſh, fowls, and every plant or green herb, and ſubjects all to man, only forbidding cruelty; as appears by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Fleſh with the life thereof, that is the blood thereof, ſhall ye not eat;</hi> and again repeats his bleſſing <hi>v.</hi> 7. And then God largly eſtabliſheth his Covenant with all creatures and men again, in <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. and then confirms it with the token of the Rainbow, from <hi>v.</hi> 13. with a great deal of very gracious inlargment and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement when they ſhall ſee that token to <hi>v.</hi> 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hence Gods Throne is compaſſed with the Rainbow, <hi>Ez.</hi> 1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4. where he gives an excellent <hi>Epephonema</hi> of his ſaid grace (as I may ſay) <hi>And God ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> Noah, <hi>this is the token of the Covenant which I have establiſhed between me and all fleſh which is upon the earth.</hi> Now as the earth with its fruitfulneſs and varieties of creatures is made the ſtage and accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation too, for all actings of promiſed and purpoſed grace from thence to the end of the world: ſo the chief and greateſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of fruitfulneſs, are reſerved for the time of Chriſts ſaid reign, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. twice, <hi>Then ſhall the earth bring forth her increaſe; and God even our God ſhall give us his bleſſings.</hi> And hence ſo many and great promiſes of thoſe kindes, upon the great Reſtauration of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi> and for both <hi>Davids</hi> houſe and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams, Iſaacs</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> then to have the Dominion. See from this Covenant a ſtrong aſſurance made thereof twice toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almoſt yet in two Viſions of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah, ch.</hi> 33. <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. <hi>If, ſaith God, ye can break my Covenant of the day, and my Covenant of the night,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Then may alſo my Covenant be broken with</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>my ſervant, that he ſhould not have a Son to reign upon his Throne,</hi> &amp;c. [that is, Chriſt ſhall moſt certainly reign as the Son of <hi>David</hi> to the end of the world] and what man ſhall dare to deny this, and make any other meaning thereof? And again, <hi>v.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>If my Covenant be not with day and night, and if I have not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the ordinances of heaven and earth. Then will I caſt away the ſeed of Jacob and David my ſervant, ſo that I will not take any of his ſeed to be rulers over the ſeed of Abraham, Iſaac and Jacob: for I will cauſe their captivity to return, and have mercy on them.</hi> Many other places may here be produced to like purpoſe, but this in brief at preſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That all thoſe Promiſes and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted Mercies made and given, to and with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to their ſpiritual ſeed, by that one Divine ſeed [Chriſt] for a thouſand Generations; which is a frequent expreſſion in holy Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.10. and particularly applyed to the promiſe and Covenant of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and ſung out by <hi>David</hi> at the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home the Arke to his Tent provided for it, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 16.8. and again recorded <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the laſt place ſaid to be the Covenant which God remembred for ever: and the word commanded for a thouſand Generations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as largly there ſet down to all three, who in the grace
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102106:5"/> they received reſembled the Trinity: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> as the fountain of mercy to his ſeed inveſted in himſelf; <hi>Iſaac</hi> as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyer thereof, in thy ſeed alone not in thee, <hi>Jacob</hi> as the immediate diſpenſer to the twelve Tribes, &amp; to <hi>Iſhmael</hi> his natural ſeed; but in conjunction with Chriſt, that what was wanting in <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould be made up in Chriſt; therefore ſaies God to him, in thee and in thy ſeed [Chriſt] ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and God often ſtiles himſelf, the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in reference to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe yet to be fulfilled to them, perſonally in their inheriting the promiſe of <hi>Canaan,</hi> called <hi>the Lot of their Inheritance,</hi> Pſal. 105.11, in the time of Chriſts Kingdom on earth: but the 1000. generations ſeems to contain 7000. years from the giving the firſt promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to the end of the world. Which Promiſe, contained in the bowels of it, all the great Promiſes made to the Fathers afterwards; and as from that Conduit head, God hath diſpoſed through thoſe water pipes of future Promiſes, his mercies to this or that perſon, family or nation as he pleaſed ever ſince; a generation being uſually reckoned 7 years, as 21 years is 3 lives, ſuitable to <hi>Davids</hi> old age of 70 years (which few of very many attain to) in the intermediat 4000. years of the world (for the ages of the old world, and of the world to come, differ for diſtinct reaſons) ſo the other ſeems to be the ſtandard, and the ſaid Promiſe or Covenant ſeems be to here ſaid to be remembred for ever, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drawn from that for the reſidue of 1000. generations, by <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> to their ſpiritual ſeed at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the juſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> untill, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, The heavens ſhall be no more, and the earth with all upon it become <hi>ve Tohu, ve Bohu, (i. e.)</hi> become again without form and void for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or a perpetual priſon. Come we firſt to <hi>Abraham</hi> that <hi>Pater excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> the Father of the faithful, to whom the ſaid grace was diſpenſed in a 7 ſold grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2, 3. and ſo forward, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereupon his ready obedience to Gods call, he made a large comprehenſive Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of that land, and all other mercies, to himſelf alone perſonally, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.18. through the Divine one ſeed [Chriſt] con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived then and afterwards, ſo by faith in <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſoul, that as our Saviour ſaid, <hi>John</hi> 8.56. <hi>Abraham ſaw my day and was glad:</hi> yea and his future day alſo of injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a far of, with <hi>Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Heb.</hi> 11. at the ſaid Reſurrection re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the deadneſs of <hi>Abrahams</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb, and <hi>Iſaacs</hi> ſaving from death in a figure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Upon his coming to <hi>Sichem</hi> God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him, and promiſed that land un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his natural ſeed, <hi>v.</hi> 7. as it is expounded <hi>c.</hi> 15.13, 14. whereof <hi>Abraham</hi> in perſon was to have no part, <hi>v.</hi> 15. nor <hi>Iſaac</hi> nor <hi>Jacob;</hi> who all died long before the 400. years ended.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When he was ſevered from <hi>Lot,</hi> God ſaid to him <hi>c</hi> 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. View all the coaſts, Eaſt, Weſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For I will give it to thee and to thy ſeed for ever; namely to his one moſt Divine ſeed Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. who ſhould continue for ever, and would retain his right, and maintain <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> Proprietie which he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for him and all his: and God bids him walk through that land then, for ſaith he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain I will give it unto thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When upon Gods great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Abraham</hi> repreſents his Age and Childleſs eſtate unto God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thereupon he bids him look up to Heaven and tell the Stars, <hi>&amp;c. c.</hi> 15.2, 3, and then ſaid he: So ſhall thy ſeed be; <hi>(i. e.)</hi> all his ſpiritual ſeed, and probably both, for number and excellencie, being circumciſed or uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed through the ſaid one seed [Chriſt] &amp; this occaſioned upon that account, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous act of his faith, ſo often mentioned; <hi>He believed in the Lord, and it was counted unto him for Righteouſneſs.</hi> Whereupon our ſo heavenly learned Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gods larg Deeds ſo ſtrongly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſtrong faith, ſettling his intereſt upon him in the world, ſtiles him the Heir of the world by faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. by which he was then ſecure, and is and will be ſince that time his intereſt therein e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to that very moment wherein he ſhall be actual poſſeſſor thereof in that world to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102106:6"/> come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. and this he largly explains in that <hi>c. Rom</hi> 4. from <hi>v.</hi> 8. to the end, ſhewing how he becomes father of the uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as well as of the circumciſion and ſets forth the excellency of his faith, which was counted to him for righteouſneſs, in giving glory to God who quickneth the dead, when his body was dead naturally, and there was deadneſs in <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb, yet knew God could call things that are not as though they were, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 16, 17, 18, 19. So that from and by ſuch a ſeed which by his faith was conceived in his ſoul ſhould proceed all his promiſed intereſt, and ſhould by him be made ſure to all his ſpiritual ſeed as the ſtars; in reſpect whereof he is here ſtiled the heir of the world, then paſt by faith but will moſt certainly then to come by actual fruition alſo be poſſeſſor thereof, <hi>v,</hi> 22, 23, 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So alſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6. upon that great act of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith reſpecting ſuch a ſeed to ſecure the real inheritance of the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed land to him and all the believing world in the time of the Law or Goſpel (for we muſt know all the Dominion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and all their then priviledges are found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in grace, and much greater grace than theſe dayes have afforded) in the laſt <hi>v.</hi> he concludes for the comfort of all truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſouls among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they have in Chriſt the ſame priviledge in that ſtate with the <hi>Jews</hi> which ſhall be the ſure enterance to all <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſpiritual ſeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal glory, for (ſaith he) if ye be <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> (ſpiritual) ſeed, then heirs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that which was made to him for that reſtored ſtate of <hi>Canaan</hi> which <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> with all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſhall moſt certainly enjoy, and all the faithful till then, ſhall alſo with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit; &amp; that in the happy reſtored ſtate of the New Heavens &amp; New Earth wherein will dwell righteouſneſs, &amp; yet to confirm to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> both an aſſured Title and Poſſeſſion in time to come (though then he ſaw it a far of by his faith.) <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And again God minds him <hi>c.</hi> 15. that for that end he brought him him out <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the <hi>Caldees</hi> to that land to inherit it; which <hi>Abraham</hi> revolves as deſiring to have a confirmation that he ſhould inherit it, <hi>v,</hi> 7.8. and thereupon he gives him a ſign by the beaſts and fowls, to be uſed as God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then firſt he explains the condition of his natural ſeed, for number as the duſt, that ſhould firſt be afflicted, &amp; a ſtranger till after 400. years which he made a promiſe to, <hi>c.</hi> 12.7 as follows, <hi>v</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17. after which, <hi>Sarah</hi> from diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence puts <hi>Hagar</hi> upon her husband whence came the ſeed of the bondwoman? as in the ſtory, <hi>c.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But afterwards, <hi>c.</hi> 17. when <hi>Abraham</hi> was 99. years of age, God appears again to him, and makes a Covenant and ſtipulation with a ſeal thereto, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumciſion then to be firſt upon his own fleſh with all the males in his family (and as in the Old world that Chriſt ſhould be the ſeed of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was the comfort of that ſex then firſt in the trangreſſion: So henceforth he was made known to be the ſeed of men lineally from <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of <hi>David,</hi> as Gods King to ſit on his holy hill of <hi>Sion, Pſ</hi> 2. as well as <hi>Davids</hi> ſon to ſit on his throne, ſtiled the <hi>the Son of man, Pſ.</hi> 80.17. that man of his right hand made ſtrong for himſelf, as alſo ſeen in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by <hi>Dan.</hi> as the ſon of man when he will come in glory in the clouds to take the ſame Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 17 13, 14, <hi>&amp;c</hi> &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 27. Hence he ſo often ſtiles himſelf <hi>the Son of man</hi> in the Goſpel, which alſo ſhould be a comfort for mans ſex, beſides other reaſons) And for mans farther aſſurance that Seal is to be upon his fleſh peculiar to his ſex till Chriſt was indeed born of a Vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as foretold <hi>Eſ.</hi> 9.7. and till God did a new thing in the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a woman ſhall compaſs a man, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.22. So then (I ſay) <hi>c.</hi> 17. God renews his confirmation of his former promiſes to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> more fully and firmly, and adds the ſaid ſeal to it, with the changes of his name and <hi>Sarahs,</hi> to ratifie the ſame, and relie him it ſhould be an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and an everlaſting Poſſeſſion, and he would be the God of him and his ſeed, to be fulfilled at Chriſts coming with his Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Covenant ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in <hi>Iſaac</hi> whom <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhould bear at this ſet time in the next year, <hi>v.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In <hi>c.</hi> 22. upon <hi>Abrahams</hi> ready obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102106:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to ſacrifice his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> after his long waiting for him and enjoyment of him, God expreſſeth his love to him paſſionatly, if I may ſo ſpeak, (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his bretheren) in a large and full manner, ratifying all by an oath, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17, 18. thereby farther to confirm all the ſaid promiſes and covenants to him and his ſeed in general, natural or ſpiritual, circumciſed or uncircumciſed; which alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he again and again confirmed to <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> particularly.</p>
               <p n="8">8. As firſt to <hi>Iſaac, c.</hi> 26.23. both for his perſon and poſterity twice, firſt when he was at <hi>Gerar,</hi> and forbids him to go into <hi>Egypt: I will,</hi> ſaid God, <hi>be with thee and bleſs thee, and give into thy hand all theſe countreys, and in thy ſeed ſhall all the nations of the earth be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, becauſe that Abraham obey'd my voice and kept my charge, my comandments, my statutes &amp; my laws.</hi> Mark theſe expreſſions, he ſaid not to him at all <hi>[in thee]</hi> as to <hi>Abraham, c</hi> 12.2, 3. but becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> had kept my charge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (probably) in regard <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithful, or <hi>Pater excelſus</hi> as his name then ſignified, had by his wonderful faith ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually conceived Chriſt in his ſoul then ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby Chriſts day and rejoyced, as our Saviour himſelf ſpeaks of him, <hi>John</hi> 8.56. and was glad, yea and God alſo again, <hi>v.</hi> 24. confirms the ſame mercies to <hi>Iſaac</hi> who was his great Type, both in his birth and death, and yet both of them with <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Sarah Heb.</hi> 11. ſaw their own particular intereſt (as was ſaid) in <hi>Canaan</hi> a far of, at the Reſurrect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, where their bodies &amp; <hi>Joſephs</hi> bones lay repoſed till they ariſe then to take their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it and reign with Chriſt, when at that his laſt day he will raiſe them up, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Laſtly, God confirms unto <hi>Jacob</hi> his perſonal intereſt in the land of <hi>Canan,</hi> and to his immediate natural ſeed the 12 Tribes, here again ſaid to be as the duſt of the earth: and hence faith God in conjunction with his Divine ſpiritual ſeed [Chriſt] again <hi>v.</hi> 14 <hi>in thee and in thy ſeed ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed,</hi> in that reſpect (probably) with his bleſſings given to the ſeveral Tribes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. and to <hi>Eſau</hi> his bleſſing alſo; being his immediate ſeed which went very far, but what might be wanting in him, was made up in that one ſeed [Chriſt] therefore he adds; <hi>[and in thy ſeed] ſhall all the families of the earth be bleſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> who will at the firſt bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection raiſe all his Saints who in their meaſure have ſuffered with him as members of his miſtical body to reign (then) with him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. and ſaith he, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>We are made by Chriſt heirs of God, and joynt heirs Chriſt; viz.</hi> in his Mediators <hi>Davidical</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom bequeathed to them by our Saviour himſelf in his laſt will a little before he died after his divinely propherical Prayer, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. ſaid he, <hi>Father I will that they whom thou haſt given me be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given me.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>c.</hi> 32. <hi>Jacob,</hi> as a Prince, wraſtled with God and prevailed, whence the name of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was given to him, retained by all Gods people ſince, to ſhew them how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with God for promiſed mercies, <hi>viz.</hi> by Faith, Prayer and New obedience, <hi>&amp;c. [See of theſe covenanted mercies Prodrom or Forerun. page</hi> 37, 38.] and God was ſo mindful of both the everlaſting Covenants which <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, &amp;c.</hi> as he calls that <hi>Gen</hi> 9.16. that by the experience of the former witneſſed by the Rainbow many hundred years after, he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the Prophet <hi>Eſau</hi> thereby to confirm his covenanted mercies to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with the beloved City. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 54 9. This ſaith he ſhall be as the waters of <hi>Noah</hi> unto me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I have ſworn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo will I not be wroth with thee: yea all that promiſed grace, <hi>v.</hi> 17. is ſaid to be the heritage of the ſervants of the Lord even from that time whoſe Righteouſneſs is of him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We proceed to the promiſed and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted mercies of <hi>David</hi> for ever, through the whole ſtate of Chriſts <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom, who ſtands in divers relations to <hi>David</hi> as his Antitype, Seed and Saviour wherein conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſure mercies of <hi>David</hi> in and by him who was the root of <hi>David, Rev.</hi> 5, as well as the branch, <hi>Zac.</hi> 3.8. who was owned to be the ſon of God at his Reſurrection, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.7. and returned not to corruption, whereby was manifeſt the ſureneſs of his mercies, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.32 33. wherein all the faithful partake, <hi>Eſ</hi> 55.3. by a covenant ordered in all things and ſure, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. though chiefly reſpecting Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, as in <hi>Nathans</hi> meſſage may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 17. &amp; 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102106:7"/> have largly conſidered in our 7th Foundation of Faith: when the heathen and the uttermoſt parts of the earth will not only be given to Chriſt for an inheritance, but for a poſſeſſion, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.8. when God ſets his King upon his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and though he is the Fathers Commiſſioner to execute the contents of the book which he received, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. from his aſcention to the ruine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, <hi>viz.</hi> during Gods ſpiritually powerful King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Stone, ſaid to be ſet up by the God of heaven, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.28. yet when the Kingdom of the Mountain comes, all oppoſite King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms will becom like the chaff of the ſummer thraſhing-flore, <hi>v.</hi> 35. for at his ceaſing to ſit at his fathers right hand his foes will eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be made his footſtoole, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.1. and that man of his right hand will appear to be made ſtrong for himſelf, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 80.17. when all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the world will be given to him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the whole heavens, <hi>Dan</hi> 2.13.14, 27. and God will give him his right in <hi>Davids</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, <hi>Ez.</hi> 21.27 and all the faithful before ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sons of <hi>David,</hi> as well as the ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> being the meek like <hi>David</hi> whoſe ſoul was as a weaned child, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 121. ſhall all then inherit the renewed earth and delight themſelves in abundance of peace <hi>Pſ</hi> 37.11. and be bleſſed in that ſtate, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. at the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. for then he will actually &amp; perſonally (as we ſhewed) take to himſelf his great power before com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or permitted to others, who had abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, and will then himſelf reign with his Saints upon the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5 10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.14, 15. when the Angels of God ſhall worſhip him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 97. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. and all knees in heaven, earth or under the earth (now) ſhall (then) bow or be ſubject to him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10. and all creatures adore him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.8, 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when not only as the ſon of <hi>David</hi> he ſhall have that Kingdom, but alſo as the ſon of God he will be actually Gods heirof all things: by his Triple right of creating, ordering and redeeming all things for that purpoſe, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3, &amp; 6. when <hi>Abraham</hi> by him, and under him will be actually heir of the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. who before was only by faith ſo: and this Kd. <hi>Dan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 7.13, 14. ſeems alſo to be ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt as Gods obedient ſon and faithful ſervant by his own Donation; as a boon or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for that he had fully done all Gods wills; and ſo he as the captain of the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſuffering members, upon the like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count gives his Kingdom to them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. making them joynt heirs with himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. &amp; bequeathed the beholding of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to them as by his laſt will, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I will, &amp;c.</hi> through whom, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſeed living in the world then, will (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be bleſſed in a ſpecial manner, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 61.9. Then will kingdom, power and glory all be his from his coming in the clouds, not only in his own glory, but alſo of the father and his holy angels, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. which he will reſign back unto the father when the laſt enemy death ſhall be deſtroyed, that God may be all in all, and the ſon alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him, when perfect reconciliation is made; Chriſt having ſo conducted all his Saints from their general rapture to meet him at their glorious change to enter upon thoſe things for ever, that eye hath not ſeen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides thee, O God, ſaith <hi>Eſay, c.</hi> 64.4. and Oh what things ſaith <hi>David</hi> with an holy admiration, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 31.19. of which an excellent improvement is made by our ſo divinely learned Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. to the end of that chap. which may be counted amongſt his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of. <hi>See Foundat.</hi> 7th.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only here, beloved Chriſtians, adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you all, of theſe three particulars. 1. That the 21. ſaid brief aſſertions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if duly weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by Gods word, may afford you ſufficient ſatisfaction as to theſe Doctrines of Chriſts ſaid reign the 1000. years upon earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That both all Gods ſaid general mercies promiſed to mankind, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. that Chriſt ſhould eminently (then) break the ſerpents head, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.1. and alſo all that ſaid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and covenanted preſervation and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to and with <hi>Noah</hi> and the New world, <hi>&amp;c. Gen.</hi> 8, 9, <hi>c.</hi> are all (then) chiefly and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be accompliſhed alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That thoſe more particular and ſpecial promiſed and covenanted mercies to <hi>Abraham Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and to all their faithful ſeed both <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> and alſo all thoſe glorious promiſed and covenanted ſure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>David,</hi> and his ſpiritual ſeed, ſhall all have their real, true, yea only future litteral, fulfillings in the ſaid Kind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Chriſt on earth.</p>
               <p>But as for their larger explications being too large for the intended compaſs of this Key, I muſt at preſent refer them to ſome future opportunity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102106:7"/>
               <head>22th. The Doctrine of Chriſts glorious Kingdom [or the New Jeruſalem State] now ſhortly approaching, is exceeding comfortable and very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to all faithfull Chriſtians, is manifest by the Key and this whole Work; and by the enſuing <hi>[Paraeneſis]</hi> or Monitory Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may further appear. <hi>Anno Dom. 1672.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd now dear Chriſtian Bretheren allow me a little freedom in this office of love, you I mean who are partakers of the grace of God purchaſed by Jeſus Chriſt and by the ſpirit of ſanctification wrought in your ſouls, whether Epiſcopal (ſo called) Presbyterian or Independent; with ſundry others upon the ſame foundation,<note place="margin">Firſt for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie.</note> many of which, through Gods eſpecial mercy, have evidently obtained like precious grace; to you all I ſpeak, as ſuch. Why do you ſtill ſtand at diſtance one from another? Conſider, I pray you, That one Heaven (as ye all believe) ſhall hereafter contain you all, when ye ſhall be made perfect in one; yea moreouer, I am well aſſured, that one Glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt to come will ſatiate all your ſouls as ſuch, a long time before you can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the other, <hi>viz.</hi> both ſouls and bodies; all whoſe degrees of bleſſedneſs is only to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in Gods beſt order, and time and manner revealed in his word; whether men take cognizance of it more particularly or leſs:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſ</hi> 64.4. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 31.19.</note> And after that great day of Judgment is finiſhed, the expectation of all Saints to attain <hi>Thoſe things which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor hath entered into the heart of man to conceive, beſides thee, O God,</hi> ſaith the Evangelical Prophet <hi>[Eſa.]</hi> And, <hi>O how great things</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>David) hath God prepared,</hi> &amp;c. But the ſtate of things in Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, is not altogether ſuch, in the interim; though very glorious, and excellent, and bleſſed, and ſuitable to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition (then,) when Judgment ſhall be given to the Saints in the world, long before the finiſhing of the laſt Judgment. And moſt of you, if not all, are one in the things, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that are counted eſſentially neceſſary <hi>[ad eſſe Eccleſiae]</hi> for the being of the Church of Chriſt: how ſhould all ſorts agreeing in the main, then alſo endeavour to be one in things that pertain <hi>[ad bene eſſe]</hi> to the well being of the ſame alſo? And I am ſtrongly (from Gods word) aſſured, that it will not be long before the Lord, in that great day which he hath foretold, will be one, and his name one; even in reſpect of ſuch uſual diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of men in our dayes, and his people ſhall then ſerve him with one ſhoulder: how then ſhould all faithful Chriſtians (what in them is) endeavour, by all good means, for Unity with the bond of peace, as well as Truth, (though that eſpecially) and ſo to meet their mercy by the way; and, if it might be, anticipate it, by ſo haſtning its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: how well would Chriſt (then) take it at all your hands? Whereas, if any ſhould ſo be found ſhort of this, that they will from ſuch diſſentments, be ſmiting their Bretheren, (though it be but with the tongue, when they can do no more;) how will they expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at that day, to Chriſts objurgation, before Angels and Men, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> Unite, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Bretheren, I ſay, Unite, Unite in one in theſe matters alſo, at leaſt in your ſpirits, and the actings of them; that may be the way, where God may ſupply what you are want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, to bring about the buſineſs (which you ſo rightly and really endeavour,) by grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Fiat</hi> in the caſe. Let each ſort caſt off their peculiar obſtacles, and any-wayes-thwarting intereſts; Complying fully with Gods Rules, that ſhould fully guide us all therein, and They, I humbly conceive, are very few, but ſufficient; only, men muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware they miſtake them not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they pervert them not in their uſe and mannagment. The firſt is that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>Let all things be done to edifying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> viz.</hi> of the ſouls of Gods people; and this is a comprehenſive and forcible rule and direction, which in every conſtitution and counſel of men, ought much to ſway the matter, is the thing pleaſing or profitable or creditable, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> that may be ſomewhat in ſome caſes, but the great Queſtion in matters of ſuch nature, as men may order, is: But is it ſo for edifying? If they will not advance that end in Gods Church, what ſhould they do there? but if they will hinder it, why ſhould they be ſuffered in it? And then a ſecond follows, <hi>v.</hi> 40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order:</hi> which two rightly applyed like our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102106:8"/> Saviours firſt and ſecond law of love, containing all the other: So may theſe being rightly mannaged, in all ſuch caſes, regulate the counſels and actings of men in Church affairs; but as love was the matter of both theſe laws (though fixt upon diſtinct octjects;) ſo edifying is the ſubſtance and the end of both, though the latter for the manner, ought often more neceſſarily to be applyed with the other, as being ſubordinate thereunto, in ſundry reſpects of nature, matter, uſe and end, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtles inſtances which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned this ſecond Rule, ſeems to teach us the right uſe of it; the one caſe of decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy whether women ſhould ſpeak in the Church; That, by the Apoſtle (authoritatively) was once and for all times, ordered negatively, as being ſpecially guided by Gods ſpirit: <hi>Let not your women ſpeak,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The other was a profitable orderly ſettling the way of their propheſieing, that it might more tend to edifycation; and contrary confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be avoyded, that would hinder the ſame: And the Apoſtle ſeems ſo to ſubordinate the latter to the firſt, as if no plea of order (or decencie at leaſt) might be approveable, but as in conjunction with in its nature, uſe or end with edifycation of the Church of Chriſt; whereby natural or prudential agreements, for times or places of worſhip, and utenſels therein, by humane and Chriſtian qualifications, may be ſuitably judged of and approved by men, <hi>[pro hic &amp; nunc,]</hi> as it is, or ought to be, with ſome Officers <hi>[quam diu ſe bene geſſerint]</hi> and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Braſen Serpent, was approved to be <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huſhtan; but ſtill by the two former rules to be examined, eſpecially, and neceſſarily by that of edifycation; for prudence and decencie, and all the other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if not qualified for edifycation, or being contrary, are (for ought I can diſcern from the Apoſtles ſaid ruled caſes) pleas without doores, in reference to ſuch ſaid conſtitutions or counſels of men in the Church of Chriſt: Whereas, for Officers and Ordinances, and what elſe is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, the Scripture gives many, &amp; large inſtructions, and Divine inſtitutions, which Perſons of prudent hearts and ſanctified Spirits, will be apt to improve well (by Divine grace duly ſought for, and rightly applyed) and the Chriſtian charity of others, herein (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly) acquieſce: But one the other part, as any appear defective in the ſaid reſpect of edifycation, or prejudicial thereunto, they may appear to be more dangerouſly enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or hurtfully obſerved, as being excentrical to the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaid boundaries of them: And in that men have walked ſo out of theſe paths of Unity, Piety and peace, what ſad effects hath Satan upon the corruption, blindneſs and interſts of men, and ſtill doth earneſtly endeavour to bring about? let every mountain ſtanding in the way of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion be endeavoured by you to be levelled, and every bond be broken in ſunder which is not of Gods allowance: But yet may not piouſly, and charitably intended incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in things ſeemingly only good (but miſtaken) be retained? and applyed to real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good improvements, which (I ſuppoſe) they may well be judged ſo to have attained their end, with advantage; True Chriſtian Charity, piety and prudence will regulate much in many like caſes; God grant them to all ſorts in theſe reſpects eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Secondly, for Piety.</note>And all ye right Chriſtianly charitable ſouls of all ſorts, how few ſo ever in theſe key-cold, yea chilled laſt dayes ye ſeem to be, you have but a little time here to bring forth your fruits of faith and love, Let the ſeaſon of your preſent being, firſt ingage you to walk cloſly with God; be much in private and ſecret communion with him your ſelves; wherein you have (if your hearts be upright in his ſight) the greateſt advantage imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable with the King of Heaven and Earth, above the favorites of earthly Princes; who ſometimes miſtake their faithfulleſt ſervants, ſometimes hear bad information againſt them, ſometimes are remote from them, or they hindred from coming to them, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and in ſome caſes and things they cannot help, (though at Gods pleaſure Kings may be potent) yet only God himſelf is Omnipotent, many wayes beyond thought: earthly Princes may fail theirs, but God will never fail nor forſake his favourites; in all times, places and companies, a good thought, purpoſe, expreſſion of heart, or word, a ſpiritual ſoliloquie, or ejaculation is very kindly taken at Gods hand from you, who will reckon ſuch ſoul actings tokens of much love &amp; ſincerity, when ſometime more weakneſs in greater ſolemnities may appear. 2. Be much in family duties prudently contrivied, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102106:8"/> ye may continue in them; ſet your houſe in order for them; be not ſlight or fickle in them, judge not your ſelves in fit garb or poſture for worldly buſineſs, without neceſſity, till God have his family worſhipt at ſuitable opportunities; a frothie profeſſion and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Religion hath of late times, much more then formerly, thruſt theſe duties out of doors, though they ſeldom have had good entertainment within, (ſave of ſome few) true piety hath been long, yea ever hitherto, <hi>[Rara avis in terris,]</hi> very ſcarce to be found; families were the firſt and uſually the beſt plantation of fruit trees in Gods Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, keep the reſolution of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> eſpecially now, againſt the floods of ungodlyneſs; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies are like to be the beſt nurſeries of ſuch young plants, for many advantages, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, endearments; much quickning to encreaſe of grace in family-worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that advantage doth wonderfully help, encourage and further the publick Miniſtry of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thence are inſtilled uſually, and preſerved too good principles, or patterns of wholſom words, with their improvements; the defect whereof is now lamentable, for the want both of private and publick Catechiſings. Do not all wiſe builders look main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their foundations? for want of this, ſo many tottering buildings ſoon reel aſide, to one error or other, or are in continual danger of falling utterly, or mouldering to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then, right Pious ſouls, ſee that your true Chriſtianity,<note place="margin">Thirdly for Charity.</note> to help forward your good account, be outwardly manifeſt in your gracious works of charity, not only to ſupply neceſſities, but to prevent evil and do good; many poor ſouls that ſtudy faith and good conſcience towards God and men, have much encountering with tentations, in a low and hard condition, by reaſon of the prevailing iniquities of the times, and the many ways of the practiſe thereof, by the licentious, who fight ſo againſt their own outward wants, by weapons of iniquity, uſing ſuch unlawful ways, and means, and practiſes which others may not, dare not, do not; yet are ſtraightened by others ſins (in ſuch caſes) their oppreſſors, upon ſuch accounts. How ſhould the ſtrong and able in eſtate, herein in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian compaſſion, help the infirmities of the weak, eſpecially in reference to their ſoul-danger thereby; or to ſee to the good education of their childeren, and that their wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and orphans (chiefly be relieved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how by ſuch charitable deeds (eſpecially with the addition of inſtructions and encouragments) might you in ſo doing draw others to Chriſt and inſtrumentally ſave their precious ſouls? conſider what, out of your Revenues you can with a chearful heart and ready hand, yearly, monthly, or weekly return to God, in a thanks-offering; by his now many, many receivers neer you, or known to you, for the all which you have received beſides; and conſider, (according to the Apoſtles rule) how God hath proſpered you the preceding week, and let that grace of an humble, thankful, true chriſtian charity, have its due operation in you in her proportion; and if rents and gains will not do it as you deſire, then cut off ſinful exceſſes in vain expences, more cloſly and barely, in too coſtly and curious apparel, laviſhing entertainments, in inconſiderat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coſtly buildings, now the world is neer her departure, by her great ſhaking fits ceiſing upon her; yet theſe are the common ſins of the times, and the breeders of mens future ſorrow, and too late repentance, when a much better and ſafer improvement ſhould have been made thereof; now you may make God your debtor, by his promiſe, and your ſelves temporally more bleſſed by giving than by receiving. If men did but caſt in a tenth of what they receive, or but even of what many vainly conſume, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into Gods treaſury, for ſuch charitable uſes, or any other like, (for the world abounds with objects of that nature) there is no queſtion, but they would find a better return, yea (haply) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better returns, of that tenth which they gave, or ſome others out of their eſtates vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſume (and that with advantage) above all the nine parts that they or ſuch others detained from ſuch offerings to God; beſides the prayers, praiſes and thankſgivings from men thereupon, which God will obſerve and reward. Let me only add this comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive conſideration for all, at preſent; That your final ſentence of approbation or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation will, by Chriſt himſelf, be paſſed mainly upon that account,<note place="margin">See Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt. Goſ. p. <hi>19, 20.</hi> where Mat. <hi>25.</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. Obſ. it well.</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. as carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it well or ill in that kind, to ſuch little ones, or diſciples of his, in <hi>relieving, viſiting, cloathing them,</hi> (which ſaith Chriſt, is done to himſelf,) but if men injure and perſecute
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102106:9"/> them, how heavy will their judgment be? but if in them Chriſtians relieve Chriſt? they muſt labour to do it, for Chriſts ſake; in faith, in obedience, out of love, out of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to the firſt giver, who made them large receivers firſt, whereupon they are much in his debt, &amp; ſhould endeavour much to come out of ſome part of it, (for which God may diſcharge in full) before death come, which cuts off further opportunitie, and impriſons all unbelievers for ſuch debts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.7.</note> [oh that men would conſider it] before the time of execution come! for then all ſuch intereſt is gone, and they leave [moſt likely] a curſe to their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, entailed on their eſtates to conſume in ſin, or give them up to ſerve Satans inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, or to make them become a prey to the devourer, or a bootie to the ſupplanter, one way or other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſuch perſons ſhould in theſe times lay to heart this conſideration for two reaſons. 1. By how much the times are more provoking of Gods wrath; ſo all eſtates are more tottering therefore it would be more wiſdom to ſecure much, whilſt ye may, by committing it to Gods ſafe inſuring hands; it may, more likely, reſcue the reſt, or keep of vengeance the longer, and ſo more time of well doing will be allowed. Again, Satan hath great wrath, becauſe his time is now very ſhort, and therefore he marcheth furiouſly with his hoſts of evil men and devils to ruin all he can; Chriſtians ſhould then likewiſe <hi>[vi &amp; armis]</hi> with all their might give him the repulſe, by laying out themſelves in their perſons, poſſeſſion, parts, poſterity, their all for Chriſt; whence two encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 1. Chriſt will ſurely give them both victory, and recompence; and the devil being reſiſted, as the greateſt coward, he will alſo flee, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7.2. As the times are very bad, ſo Chriſtians help is more needful; and the rather, becauſe we are fallen into the dregs of bad times, when upon many weighty conſiderations, we may expect Chriſts coming very ſhortly, and the beſt that live now and lawfully enjoy plentiful eſtates, know not whether they or theirs ſhall retain [then] any of the things which they now poſſeſs: yet let ſuch take this conſolation, that they and their poſterity being faithful will gain by that change in this world, when one in a bed, in the field, in the mill, by the Angels will be carried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the 4 quarters of the earth, to Chriſt as their arke, or as the Eagles to the carkaſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.28. and planted in a better ſoile, and much better eſtate, to inherit the mercies promiſed to the fore-fathers,<note place="margin">See Obſ. <hi>20.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Tract. on Rev. <hi>20, 22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I pray God ſanctifie ſuch as here them, by theſe Divine truths thus briefly hinted; and let me to that end, offer this caution to all ſerious Chriſtians, to take heed leſt (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old entered not into <hi>Canaan</hi> becauſe of unbelief) that their unbelief [if not their ſlighting of theſe Divine truths] cauſe not Chriſt in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to bring them late into the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate at the firſt bleſſed Reſurrect. when, as ſome antients conceived, there will be <hi>[mora]</hi> to ſome, though I doubt not but all the faithful till then, [and not only actual Martyrs] will have ſome part in that ſtate longer or ſhorter, it is dangerous to contemn or oppoſe any Divine truths ſuch as theſe are; [and as I from good ground know theſe to be.] As for meaner Chriſtians I only ſay this,<note place="margin">See Satans ſeven Vials. Forerunner p. <hi>41, 42.</hi>
                  </note> which is much in few words, let them walk in their general and particular cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, wherein they are called, with God faithfully, they then will have this ſtrong ſupport that he wil not fail them nor forſake any of them, and to that end conſider what is ſaid before concerning theſe laſt times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Other improvements of theſe truths we briefly hinted in our Pract. pieces on <hi>Gen</hi> 3.15. <hi>Rev</hi> 22 20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which with this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation I leave to Chriſtians uſe and Gods bleſſing; praying at preſent, after that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients mode with ſome addition.</p>
               <floatingText type="prayer">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Domine Jeſu ſi qua pro tenuitate mea in his ſcripſi, quae mea ſunt, non tua, tuip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ignoſce mihi; omnia autem quae tua ſunt, a me tam indigno, hic prolata agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant etiamque tui.</hi> Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>(i. e.)</hi> L. Jeſus, if I have in theſe things written any out of mine own meaneſs, wch are my own, but not thine, pardon thou me therein, but let thy ſerv. alſo acknowledg all thoſe things wch are thine own, though here tendred to them by ſo unworthy a perſon as my ſelf. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Tit. p. 1. K. for Χ p. 7 r. <hi>Tohu vabohu.</hi> Word Writ. r. 3. <hi>Vaus</hi> for 3. <hi>Zains.</hi> in fold. leaves r. <hi>reunited</hi> not <hi>recruted. builder</hi> not <hi>redeemer, vailed</hi> not <hi>railed.</hi> in S. of <hi>Dan.</hi> 366. not 666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102106:9"/>
            <head>An account of the compoſing and Parcels contained in this Book: with ſome Apologetical hints. <hi>July 27. 1672.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. FIrſt in general, obſerve from the beginning of the general Title page, and the leaf next following, where the nature and uſe of all parts is ſhewed, that thoſe books there called the Principles, namely, thoſe firſt three of the four parts Printed before the burning of <hi>London, An. Dom.</hi> 1666. of which, neer 600. of ſeveral ſorts were burnt and loſt: <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Prodromus,</hi> the <hi>Irenicon</hi> and <hi>Parallel,</hi> contain many things which are Eſſays of myſterious Diſcoveries containing much matter of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as in the 16. Divine Theſ. p. 3, 4 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>Iren.</hi> 6. Inferences following are deduced: and from the 4, &amp; 5. <hi>c.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> p. 9. enſuing to <hi>p.</hi> 33. (wherein many obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable things are contained) are 7. other pertinent Inferences drawn: So alſo Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments from the Scripture ſence of the Lords Prayer, and Articles of Faith, <hi>p.</hi> 90 91. of <hi>Iren. &amp;c.</hi> 2. Obſerve in general, that from the varietes of the Diſcoveries in the ſaid three books were by a ſpecial hand of Providence thoſe 8 comprehenſive convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Arguments deduced in [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] or the <hi>Word Written,</hi> which as ſtrangly was publiſhed (as might be ſhewed:) whereunto likewiſe very many upon like account might be added, as being in like manner couched in ſuch myſterious Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and obſervable paſſages upon many occaſions therein contained; and many from the 31. Uſeful obſervations to underſtand myſtical Propheſies after the Tract. on <hi>Rev.</hi> 22, 20. I might here add others from the nature and end of theſe Doctrines, as that they are Homogeneal Harmonious and uniform with all other Chriſtian Doctrines, <hi>p.</hi> 50. to the end, not new, but only Scriptural explications of the Old; Aſſert, eight of the Key, and from the end of them, <hi>viz.</hi> the fulfilling of the promiſed mercies to the Fore-Fathers, <hi>p.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 10. I have obſerved 4 places in Scripture Divinity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe Doctrines naturally fall in: otherwiſe there will be a Chaſme and void place from Scripture grounds obſervable. Firſt the Conſideration of the general Execution of Chriſts 3 Offices is to precede the particular as being the chief part of that well grounded diſtinction in the 11, and 12. Divine Theſis, in <hi>p.</hi> 5, 6. of the <hi>Irenicon.</hi> 2dly, Sacred Scripture teacheth, that after Chriſt hath ſatisfied for ſin, riſen again, aſcended, and ſitten the appointed time at the right hand of God on his Fathers Throne, till he make his foes his footſtool: then he will begin to ſit on his own Throne, at his coming the 2d time without ſin, only for Salvation to all his People, to perform that Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the raiſed Sts. even the Redemption of their Bodies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. by freeing them from the corruption of the grave, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And 2dly, all thoſe alive from all their enemies [both Men and Devils] to ſerve God without ſo much as fear of them, all the dayes of their lives, <hi>Luke</hi> 1 71. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to redeem even the inferiour creatures from the bondage of corruption [from Men or other Creatures] into the glorious, <hi>&amp;c. viz.</hi> in their capacity in that ſtate of the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.22. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. <hi>See for this in the Everlaſting Goſpel on</hi> Gen. 3.19. <hi>p.</hi> 8. <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>particular there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3dly, From the Scripture explication of the Lords Prayer, that his Name may be then hallowed in earth as it is now, and till then in heaven: and ſo his Kingdom may come and will be done in earth [then] as in heaven [now]: which will be perfectly done upon the coming of that Kingdom by Angels and raiſed Sts. in that world, and by others then alive in a very great meaſure. <hi>See p.</hi> 90, 91. <hi>of the</hi> Iren. <hi>and</hi> New Jer. <hi>p.</hi> 4, 15 <hi>the first <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4thly, It is in part the end of that ſtate both of the faith and hope of many of Gods ſervants who now groundedly both believe and hope for, ſuch their intereſt in that ſtate of the promiſed mercies to the Fore-Fathers, as we ſhewed largly in our Key, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part of Cſts. Purchaſe, and of the Sts. inheritance for ſo long a time; of which, much is ſaid in Scripture, <hi>&amp;c. See the Key of the covenanted mercies to the Fore-Fathers and their</hi> (ſpiritual) ſeed, (as we here touch) but that which in gnneral we ſhall only here far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet down, as to the former Argum. is this one moſt comprehenſive Foundation of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102106:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Multitudes of particular Arguments, in ſeveral kinds, from ſeveral ſorts of Subjects, conſidered in the whol work; namly, [That Doctrine is Divine truth, which hath not only clear Scriptures for the nature and ſubſtance of it, and for all uſeful and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table parts and branches of it, but alſo for the diſtinct and clear handling of both it &amp; them from Scripture foundations, and this farther [which is yet of very great waight where the faith thereof is wrought] that theſe Doctrines are only in ſubſtance the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed mercies to the Fore-Fathers, <hi>Ab. Iſ.</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and all their ſpiritual ſeed, both circumciſed and uncircumciſed for that ſtate in ſpecial through that one Divine ſeed Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. to be fulfilled in that world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36. in the time of the New Heavens and New Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is the time of Chriſts great day of Judgment, and of his Davidical Kingdom, which is another ſtrong foundation of the ſame promiſed mercies of all the ſpiritual Sons and Daughters of <hi>David</hi> through and with Chriſt himſelf then in that world.] I might add many others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But now for the firſt ſaid members, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſubſtance and main branches of theſe Doctrines that have clear Scripture grounds, that he that runs may read, in the whoſe work: but for the 3d, which is the diſtinct handling of thoſe things ſome may queſtion; therefore amongſt the many diſtinctions in our Key (whereof many were not before this work obſerved that I knew of) I ſhall inſtance in the two <hi>New Jeruſalems,</hi> one the immediate work of God to be made by himſelf their for the Saints raiſed after Chriſts appearance or coming, <hi>Heb</hi> 11.10, 16. and deſcribed gloriuoſly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. which is not the future glory of heaven (as formerly miſtaken) for fifteen reaſons <hi>&amp;c. See</hi> New Jeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 9, 10, 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The other made by men for the converted Jews and Gentiles, as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith expreſly by Strangers and their Kings, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60.9. <hi>See New Jeruſ.</hi> 6, 7. and for the 4th. member that for thoſe promiſed mercies to the ſaid Fore-Fathers, and <hi>David</hi> will then be accompliſhed to all the Elect, that have lived before, or ſuffered with or for Chriſt before that his 2d coming in the clouds of Heaven; and that they ſhall have their reſt with the Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. and be rewarded then, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18, 19. and all ſuch have their part in all that promiſed mercy in that ſtate, our grounds of thoſe covenanted mercies after the preparatorie: 21 aſſertions laid down in the Key, may ſufficiently (if well conſidered) I conceive, ſatisfie all ſerious unprejudiced, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſtians, which I doubt not, to ſuch may much more be made evident, from divine Authority; and theſe things would be greatly enquired into, if Chriſtians (but compently) knew and believed ſuch their own mercy and intereſt in that ſtate with Chriſt in that long continued, excellent, holy and happy condition which he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for them, and gives them intereſt in with himſelf, being joynt heirs thereof with himſelf. A large volume might be written, and to good effect, on theſe 3 Articles to this end: 1. of Chriſts coming to that firſt judicial act of Judgm. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. above 1000. years before the laſt trump, and raiſing of the wicked; ſuddainly (as probable) after the faithful that departed in the 1000 years, as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.20. 2dly, of the communion of Sts. both raiſed and living. 3dly, of the reſurrection of the juſt only; and all from good ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture warrant, if thoſe obſtacles mentioned in Aſſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 10. of the <hi>Key</hi> were not too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the world, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but theſe hints may here ſuffice in general. Now we come to the particular conſideration of the parts and parcels, with things obſervable and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to be pointed out to thoſe wiſe ſpecified, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. and to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move ſuch hinderances in their way (though from many others it ſeems not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. 1. The <hi>Irenicon,</hi> or peaceable conſideration of Chriſts Kingdom, was at firſt the only book intended (as by the method thereof ſet down <hi>chap</hi> 1. <hi>p</hi> 2. may appear) which being peruſed by many judicious perſons in thoſe ſtudies, and eſpecially by that one well known, and well approved Mr. <hi>Tho Pecke</hi> (whoſe Teſt is ſet at the end of it) after many incitements thereunto, was Printed with the <hi>Prodromus, An. Dom.</hi> 1665. which <hi>Prodr.</hi> much conſiſting of many occaſional uſeful matters after put together, and the Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof being much encouraged, was as a porch to the houſe, afterwards joyned to the <hi>Iren.</hi> and uſefully there quoted. The firſt mainly remarkable matter therein is the 16. divine <hi>Thoſes, p</hi> 9, 10, 11. introducing that great foundation of diſtinguiſhing from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102106:10"/> ſcripture warrant, the conſideration of Chriſts execution of his 3 great Offices in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of his Univerſal Church under the old and new Teſtament, and world to come, from the particular, in reſpect of every believing ſoul; the firſt as the work the Father gave him to do: the other, as the improvement or application of that work by his holy Spirit: upon which great Scripture ground that firſt Practical Treatiſe on <hi>Gen</hi> 3 15. was compoſed, in which much may be obſerved of very great weight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though I found nothing written before of that matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Paper, <hi>p.</hi> 14, 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> being more fully handled in our next practic. Tract on <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. therefore I ſay here no more of it; where the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the <hi>New Jeruſ.</hi> the immediate work of God provided for the Fore-Fathers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10 16. is explained<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in which the Elect that died before, ſhall have their part, as differing from thoſe of the nations that are ſaved, who ſhall walk in the light thereof, <hi>Rev</hi> 21. ſo <hi>Aſſertion</hi> 14. in the Key, of which little before found. The 3d is the letter to Mr. <hi>Cal.</hi> ſhewing the order and times (in a latitude) of the Seals, Trumpets, and Vials in the <hi>Rev.</hi> as a preparative to the Parallel. <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 22, 23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then there was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto the former, as a ſupplement to it [for both joyntly give much light to the book of <hi>Rev.</hi>] the larg Paper of <hi>Dec</hi> 7 64. <hi>p.</hi> 26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> concerning two defects in Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> [otherwiſe good] book of <hi>Scotland,</hi> wherein many material things are couch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 44: procedure is made to finiſh the 16 <hi>Theſes</hi> in the 3d period, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Laſtly was added the Paper of <hi>Sept.</hi> 27. 64. <hi>p.</hi> 47. of the perſonal appearance of Chriſt. <hi>Of which, ſee much more, to prove both that, and the perſonal reign, Aſſer.</hi> 7 <hi>of the Key, where much is ſaid thereof in a little room,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Iren.</hi> forenamed, obſerve in the begining, the uſeful table of Chronology, with the Preface, and the Advertiſment, ſhowing the occaſion of the anſwers, to the reaſons againſt Chriſts perſonal reign in <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 35, 36, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but in <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 2. is the method of that book, and in <hi>c.</hi> 2. with the 16 forenamed divine <hi>Theſes,</hi> are joyned 6 inferences drawn from them, from <hi>p.</hi> 3. to <hi>p.</hi> 9. unto which were ſubjoyned in the ſame <hi>chap.</hi> many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable diſcoveries of Myſteries, from <hi>Rev</hi> 4, &amp; 5. <hi>chap.</hi> with 7. inferences from the ſame, from <hi>p</hi> 9. to <hi>p.</hi> 35. of <hi>c.</hi> 3. (as we have a little before ſhewed.) In <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 41, 42. are the 6. ſeveral ſenſes of Chriſts comings in Scripture, well approved of by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Tho. Peck,</hi> to which, 2 other are added in our Key <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 6. in the fift ſence many texts of the Apoſtles are applyed <hi>p.</hi> 44, 45. to 38. but the 6th is explained in the note, page the laſt of the <hi>Word Written,</hi> alſo many Teſtimonies of the laſt times from the Apoſtles <hi>Peter, James, John,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> to all which 4 Chriſt appeared gloriouſly, as <hi>p.</hi> 49, 50, 51, 52, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In <hi>c.</hi> 5. are Satans three <hi>Babels</hi> defeated in order by God, and all which, Chriſt in his reign will bring to utter confuſion; <hi>not obſerved elſe where.</hi> Threien alſo is ſhewed according to that Foundation <hi>he ſpake by all the holy Prophets,</hi> Act. 3.21. how God ſpake by <hi>Enoch, Jude</hi> 14. by <hi>Jacob, Gen</hi> 49. by <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32, 33. &amp; <hi>Lev.</hi> 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by <hi>Balaam, Numb</hi> 24. of the latter days. The reſt of the Prophets Teſtimonies are contained, <hi>c.</hi> 6. and the larg evidences from the book of <hi>Pſalms, c.</hi> 7. according as our Saviour ſaid in <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Pſalms,</hi> it was written of me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Unto theſe are added the concurring teſtimonies in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>Acts, c.</hi> 8. [the Apoſtles witneſſings were ſpoken of before, <hi>c.</hi> 4 <hi>p.</hi> 44, 45. to 48, 49, 50, 51, 52.] which general Argument being our third in the <hi>Word Written,</hi> I have not found elſe where explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed [as for <hi>Jonah,</hi> beſides his being a Type of Chriſt, and foretelling the deſtruction of <hi>Niniveh,</hi> as Chriſt will deſtroy the <hi>Aſſyrian, (i. e.)</hi> he who ſhall be in his place at that time, as we have here to our purpoſe moſt remarkably ſpoken of, 2 <hi>King,</hi> 14. and in <hi>p</hi> 90, 91, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the Arguments from the Lords Prayer and Articles of Faith, to <hi>p.</hi> 97. where laſtly is adjoyned the Appendix of the firſt bodily reſurrection, concerning which, I having made enquiry What was written of it before, but finding nothing conſiderable, drew up that Appendix to that effect. And ſo we briefly come to the 3d part, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo Principles or Foundations; namely, the Parallel of the witneſſings of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloved Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> and of <hi>John</hi> the dearly beloved Diſciple, Evangeliſt, and moſt Seraphical Dr. of Divinity, and alſo a Prophet, largly endued with the ſpirit of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102106:11"/> Propheſie in his double book of the <hi>Rev.</hi> containing the Seal Propheſie of the civil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie: and 2d the little book Propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtick affairs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie; from both whoſe double Teſtimony, Gods ſpirit hath laid down (though divinely miſtical) the moſt ſtrong, and many waies wonderful and excellent evidence and confirmation of theſe Doctrines of the world to come, above all others; and left on purpoſe, to be the inquiring Chriſtians Key of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies; and for the profitable uſing of the ſame Key, we have endeavoured in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traced path, to manifeſt the book of <hi>Rev.</hi> to be a Divine myſtical comment upon the hidden part of <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſealed and ſhut up till the times of the end, when in the <hi>Rev.</hi> Chriſt ſo unſealed them, and commanded <hi>John</hi> to leave them unſealed, <hi>c.</hi> 22. 10. And for the uſe of this very helpful inſtrument, was the ſaid Parallel intended: Firſt, to be ſhort, as the 4th head in our ſaid method, which we found afterwards neceſſary to make a part by it ſelfe; yet as an additional ſuppliment to the <hi>Iren.</hi> as <hi>p.</hi> 1. of it, and it being as a ſtandard, rightly taken from Scripture Texts, was apt ſo to diſcover ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry mens former miſtakes (as by the fift Aſſertion in the Key, with the reference there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, may be manifeſt) and as a preparative to the ſaid Parallel, are ſet down, the ſum and order of the Seals, Trumpets and Vials in the <hi>Rev.</hi> in the foreſaid letter to Mr. <hi>Cal. Prod p.</hi> 22. and the intendment of the forenamed 2 prophetical books; <hi>viz.</hi> the Seal Propheſie, and the Book Propheſie in the <hi>Iren p.</hi> 26, 27. where obſerve with Mr. <hi>Pecke</hi> that note of the book in the margent: and ſince ſo many hundred of both the <hi>Prod.</hi> and <hi>Iren.</hi> were burnt, I drew up the Scheme of the <hi>Rev.</hi> now joyned with the <hi>Summary</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> to be placed before the <hi>Abridg.</hi> of <hi>Dan.</hi> Prophetical Viſions, as being all 5 very uſeful preparatives for the right underſtanding and improvement of the Parallel of both Books one with another, which both witneſs the ſame divine Truths of theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and, though without conſiderable pains that skill will not be like to be attained: for (as Gold and Jewels are hidden deep in the Earth and Sea) ſo that much better Treaſure of ſpiritual and divine Wiſdom, <hi>viz.</hi> the underſtanding (competently) theſe divine Truths, is with much pains and induſtry to be ſearched out and digged up; ſince the ſame divine hand that hath ſo deeply hidden both, doth ſo point out unto men what diligence they muſt uſe that will obtain them. It may be ſufficient for ſome to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſubſtance of theſe Doctrines concerning the promiſed mercies to the fore-fathers, and their ſpiritual ſeed reſpecting that ſtate: but ſuch as have opportunity and ability, eſpecially Miniſters, ought to be skilful in all the parts of their conveyance; as in the end of the Key, upon the faithful and humble ſearching whereof, much divine light and comfort may be attained, &amp;c. but this hath much more encouragment of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants,</hi> Pſ. 25.14. <hi>[Heb.] His Covenant to make them know it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> of which, this is a choice part, and in that diſcovery of ſuch coveynanted mercies opened in the Key, and in the iſſue of Revelation Propheſie, to be fully accompliſhed in the world; and will much fit all Sts. <hi>for the things not ſeen nor heard, nor which have not entered into the heart to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> for eternity after Chriſts laſt coming or deſcending from heaven, <hi>Theſ</hi> 4.16. of which coming, with the reſt named, <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 41, 42. of the <hi>Iren.</hi> was that laſt practical piece upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. which only remained now to have an account given of it, which will be beſt done of that, and of other Practicals, by due peruſals of it and them which with the 31. Obſervations, and Anſwers following, with all the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Premiſſes I now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to the pious Chriſtian Readers care, and Gods bleſſing: Unto which end I deſire with all chearfulneſs, to afford my aſſiſtance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after all, obſerve 2 things; Firſt, that many matters be handled 3 times in the whole work. 1. As diſcoveries of Myſteries. 2. As Inferences and Arguments drawn from them. 3. As Practicals and Improvements, and all uſefully and needfully enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the books are thus in order; 1. The <hi>Key (with this Account)</hi> containing the Marrow of the work. 2. The <hi>General Title Page,</hi> the Cream of all Evidence of Chriſts Kingdom. 3. The Subſtance of Argument from the Principles in thoſe 3, <hi>viz.</hi> 4. The <hi>Prodromus.</hi> 5. The <hi>Irenico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> to which, 6. the <hi>Scheme</hi> with the 7. the <hi>Parallel</hi> are annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 8. The <hi>Everlaſting Goſpels,</hi> 1. part on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. 9. Its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. part on <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. 10. The <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> on <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102106:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
